<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on GN</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on GN</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>तुरीय का अर्थ है</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/turiye/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/turiye/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;आध्यात्म में “तुरीय” (Sanskrit: तुरीय) का अर्थ है “चौथा”। यह एक अवस्था का वर्णन करता है जो जाग्रत (जागने), स्वप्न (सपने देखने) और सुषुप्ति (गहरी नींद) के पार है। तुरीय अवस्था को आत्मा की शुद्ध चेतना या परम वास्तविकता माना जाता है।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तुरीय का उल्लेख मुख्य रूप से उपनिषदों और अद्वैत वेदांत में किया गया है। यह अवस्था:&#xA;1.&#x9;चेतना से परे है: इसे शारीरिक, मानसिक और बौद्धिक अवस्थाओं से परे माना जाता है।&#xA;2.&#x9;अद्वैत (गैर-द्वैत) है: इसमें द्वैत या द्वंद्व (जैसे सुख-दुःख, अच्छा-बुरा) नहीं होता। यह शुद्ध अद्वैत अनुभव है।&#xA;3.&#x9;शुद्ध आत्मा का अनुभव: इसे “साक्षी” या “द्रष्टा” की स्थिति के रूप में समझा जाता है, जहाँ व्यक्ति अपने वास्तविक स्वरूप (आत्मा) को पहचानता है।&#xA;4.&#x9;अविभाज्य और अनंत: तुरीय अवस्था अनंत शांति, आनंद और चेतना का अनुभव कराती है।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Hugo XMin</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;XMin&lt;/strong&gt; is the first Hugo theme I have designed. The original reason that I wrote it was I needed a minimal example of Hugo themes when I was writing the  &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;blogdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; book. Basically I wanted a simple theme that supports a navigation menu, a home page, other single pages, lists of pages, blog posts, categories, tags, and RSS. That is all. Nothing fancy. In terms of CSS and JavaScript, I really want to keep them minimal. In fact, this theme does not contain any JavaScript code at all, although on this example website I did introduce some JavaScript code (still relatively simple anyway). The theme does not contain any images, either, and is pretty much a plain-text theme.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
